Inventory of the Edward Ellis Smith papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Edward Ellis Smith papers
1879-1983
82026
Hoover Institution Archives
12 manuscript boxes, 8 card file boxes (6.4 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, notes, printed matter, bibliographies, and photographs relating to the tsarist Russian secret police, the youth of Joseph Stalin, Roman Malinovskii (Malinovsky), and the history of Soviet espionage. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Smith, Edward Ellis, 1921-1982.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Edward Ellis Smith was a historian, writer, foreign service officer, and CIA agent. After graduating from West Virginia University in 1939, he was deployed to Germany to serve in World War II. Following the end of the war, he was chosen to attend Naval Language School, where he became fluent in Russian. From 1946 until 1947, he attended Strategic Intelligence School at the Pentagon and Counter Intelligence School at Camp Holabird.
Smith began work at the American Embassy in Moscow after graduation, serving as the assistant military and economic attaché. In 1950 he was appointed by United States Army Intelligence to serve as Section Chief, managing the Soviet economic and political section and analyzing policies on Soviet affairs. Towards the end of 1953, he resigned to become an intelligence officer for the CIA and completed various missions throughout Moscow. After working as a secret agent, Smith served as a Foreign Service Officer from 1954 until 1956, where he analyzed economic trends in the Soviet Union. He then served as a consultant and project manager until 1962, leading teams of specialists to work on various economic policies, such as the Marshall Plan.
Following his extensive career in the United States government, Smith pursued a full-time profession lecturing and writing. He wrote extensively for periodicals and published two historical books, both focused on Russian history, particularly Joseph Stalin and the Okhrana. From 1970 until 1980, Smith was an international economist and later vice president of Crocker Bank. He spent his final years working for Smith Bellingham International Incorporated until his sudden death in 1982.
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, correspondence, notes, printed matter, bibliographies, and photographs relating to the tsarist Russian secret police, the youth of Joseph Stalin, Roman Malinovskii (Malinovsky), and the history of Soviet espionage.
When possible, Smith's original folder titles were maintained, though some have been edited for clarity.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Malinovskii, Roman Vatslavovich, 1876-1918.; Russia. Okhrannye otdeleniia.; Stalin, Joseph, 1879-1953.; Espionage, Russian.; Secret service--Russia.; Secret service--Soviet Union.
- "The Department of Police: 1911-1913," Recollections of Nikolai Vladimirovich Veselago, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Shpanov, Nikolai, First Blow, completed translation, part 1 of 2, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Shpanov, Nikolai, First Blow, completed translation, part 2 of 2, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Shpanov, Nikolai, First Blow, rough translation, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
- "Survey of the Project at the Hoover Institution on the Tsarist and Soviet Intelligence Police, Security, and Intelligence Forces," typed essay, 1961 May 14 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- "Study of a Secret Political Police in Action," typed essay outline, 1961 July (Box-folder 1: 6)
- "Stalin and Terror," speech, 1963 January 29 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Additional footnotes and bibliography items, 1967 March 12 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Notes and research about Stalin and the Terror, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Malinovsky: Material and correspondence mail, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Martynov project, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains memoranda for the record of the Hoover Institution's efforts to broaden the Martynov papers collection and letters sent to local museums, including the Museum of Russian Culture in San Francisco, for this same reason.
- Photograph negatives, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Stuttgart Conference, 1951 August 20 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Vesselago project, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 14-15)
  Includes notes, correspondence, schedules, itinerary, expense report, memorandum for the record, and calculations of hours spent on project.
- "Todriia, sil'vestr iaseevich 1880-1936," Bol'shaia Sovetskaia Entsiklopediia, 1956 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Gruziia v Datakhm 1900-1917, chronology, 1961 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- Laroslavskii, E. V., "Vazhneishie vekhi zhizni I deiatel'nosti tovarischa Stalina,", 1939 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- Vetodhkin, M., "V sibirskoi ssylke," Istoricheskii Zhurnal, no. 1, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Nekotorye Daty, 1879-1951 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Keller, B. A., "Na putiakh mirovoi istorii," Oktiabr', no. 12, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Miliukov, P. N., "Stalin," Posledniia Novosti, 1936 December 16 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Liapidevskii, A., "Velikii strateg revoliutsii," Oktiabr', no. 12, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Golubovich, V., "Molodoi stalin, obzor vospomin" Istorik-Marksist, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Zhukov, "Gori-tbilisi," Novyi Mir, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Salisbury, Harrison, "Review of Payne's Stalin," Saturday Review, 1965 December 11 (Box-folder 2: 11)
- Yaroslavskii, E., "Tri vstrechi," Pravda, p. 4, 1939 December 23 (Box-folder 2: 12)
- Obit - Uratadze, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 13)
- Tsiavlovskii, Bol'sheviki, undated (Box-folder 2: 14)
- "Stalin et ses ennemis," Le Monde Slave, 1933 June (Box-folder 2: 15)
- Sagirashvili, D., "Stalin iz vospominanii i razmyshlenii," Vestnik Instituta Po Izucheniiu SSSR, no. 2, 1954 (Box-folder 2: 16)
- "The First of May 1901 in Tbilisi," Izvestiia, no. 100, 1937 April 27 (Box-folder 2: 17)
- Stalin's arrests, escapes and travels, 1902-1917 (Box-folder 2: 18)
- Ludwig, E., "Maitre absolu de la Russie des Soviets," La Politique, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 19)
- Kristof, L., "Boris I. Nicolaevsky," The Russian Review, no. 3, 1966 July 3 (Box-folder 2: 20)
- Kaminskii and Vereshchagin, "Detstvo i lunost'vozhdia," Molodaia Guardiia, no. 12, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 21)
- Shvarts, Semyen, I. I., undated (Box-folder 2: 22)
- Knickerbocker, H. H., "Stalin Mystery Man Even to His Mother, Post Interviewer Finds," New York Evening Post, 1930 December 1 (Box-folder 2: 23)
- Stalin miscellaneous, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 2: 24)
- Orlov, Aleksandr, "The Ghastly Secrets of Stalin's Power,", undated (Box-folder 2: 25)
- "Iz vospominanii russkago uchitelia pravoslavnoi gruzinskoi dukhovnoi seminarii," Mocka, 1907 (Box-folder 2: 26)
- Aronson, Gregory, "Was Stalin a Tsarist Agent?," The New Leader, 1956 August 20 (Box-folder 2: 27)
- Istoricheskii Zhurnal, no. 1, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 28)
- Arsenidze, R., "Iz vospominanii o Staline,", undated (Box-folder 2: 29)
- Iremashvili, I., "Stalin und die Tragodie Georgiens: Erinnerungen," Verfasser, typed translated excerpts, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 30)
- "Arkhivnye materialy o revoliutsionnoi feiatel'nosti I.V. Stalina," Krasnyi Arkhiv, 1908-1913 (Box-folder 2: 31)
- Davis, Jerome, "Joseph Stalin, Russia's Ruler Today,", undated (Box-folder 2: 32)
- Crankshaw, "The Coup that Changed the World," New York Times Magazine, 1967 February (Box-folder 2: 33)
- "Avlabar, shkola filerov" Byloe, no. 3, 1906-1917 (Box-folder 2: 34)
- "Avlabarskaia nelegal'naia tipografiia kavkazskogo soiuznogo komiteta RSDRP 1903-1906," Tbilisi: Gosizdat Gruzinskoi SSR, 1954 (Box-folder 2: 35)
- Levine, Isaac D., "Stalin Was a Tsarist Agent,", 1956 (Box-folder 2: 36)
- Possony comments on Stalin book, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 2: 37)
- Stalin miscellaneous, 1959-1966 (Box-folder 2: 38)
- "Editor Remarks," Izvestiia, 1937 April 28 (Box-folder 2: 39)
- Sharikov, K., "Vazhneishie mesta prebyvaniia i revoliutsionnoi deiatel'notsi I. V. Stalina v Peterburge-Petrograde-Leningrade,", 1909-1934 (Box-folder 2: 40)
- "Enukidze shaumyan," Pravda, 1962 May 19 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- "Orakhelashvili shaumyan," Pravda, 1963 June 10 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- Anti Komintern documents on Stalin, 1939 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- "Yerivan Expropriation," Le Temps, 1907 June 28 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Antirelioznik, no. 12, p. 17-21, 1939 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Sumbadze, L. Z., Gori, 1950 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Nadezhdin, P. P., Description of Gori, 1901 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- Bol'shaia Sovetskaia Entsiklopediia, Moskva, vol. 12, 1952 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- Bol'shaia Sovetskaia Entsiklopediia, Moskva, vol. 17, Gori, 1930 (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Shengelaia, D., "V Gori,", 1893 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- Nikulin, L., "Domik v sepukhova," Pravda, p. 5, Stalin's headquarters, 1939 December 19 (Box-folder 3: 11)
- Stalin: Raffalovich, S., "The Youth of Stalin," Miroir du Monde, 1935 July 20 (Box-folder 3: 12)
- Stalin: Scheffer, Paul, "Stalin's Power," Foreign Affairs, 1930 (Box-folder 3: 13)
- Stalin: Gunther, John, "Stalin," Harper's Monthly Magazine, 1935 (Box-folder 3: 14)
- Stalin's pre-1917 means of travel: time schedules, etc., 1899-1917 (Box-folder 3: 15)
- Written comments and notes regarding the Portrait de Staline, written by Victor Serge, 1965 (Box-folder 3: 16)
- Wells, H. G., notes from Marxism vs. Liberalism, an Interview, undated (Box-folder 3: 17)
- Grigorian, V., "Rasskazy starykh rabochikh o velikom vozhde," Tbilisi: Zaroa Vostoka, 1937 (Box-folder 3: 18)
- Nevskii, V., "Materialy dlia biograficheskogo slovaria sotsial-demokratov, vstupivshikh v rossiiskoe rabochee dvizhenie za period ot 1880 do 1905," Gosudarstvennoe Izdat, Moscow, 1923 (Box-folder 3: 19)
- "Stalin's Son," New York Times, 1962 May 19 (Box-folder 3: 20)
- van Briessen, Burmeister, and Passin, "The End of Forced Labour?," Encounter, 1956 (Box-folder 3: 21)
- "Shaumian Art on Spandarian," Izvestiia, 1962 December 15 (Box-folder 3: 22)
- Istorik-Marksist, no. 9, p. 3-26, 1940 (Box-folder 3: 23)
- Lado Ketskhoveli, 1938 (Box-folder 3: 24)
- Rudnev, D., "V sol'vychegodsk," Pravda, p. 3, 1939 December 16 (Box-folder 3: 25)
- Savinov, V., "Za narvskoi zastavoi," Vospominaniia starogo putilovtsa, Pravda, 1939 December 16 (Box-folder 3: 26)
- Pesinika, E., "V naryme," Pravda, p. 3, place of exile, 1939 December 26 (Box-folder 3: 27)
- Polevoi, no. 9, p. 4-16, 1930 (Box-folder 3: 28)
- "Rasskazy krest'ian s. kureiki o tovarishche Staline," Pravda, p. 4, 1939 December 18 (Box-folder 3: 29)
- "From the Past of Stalin," Vozrozhdenie, 1929 January 13 (Box-folder 3: 30)
- Sovetskii Muzei, no. 4, 1939 (Box-folder 3: 31)
- "Stalin I. V. k desiatiletiiu," Pravda, 1922 May 5 (Box-folder 3: 32)
- Gertik, Dina, "1912-1914 Godov," Pravda, 1927 May 6 (Box-folder 3: 33)
- Poletaev, N., "Piatnadtsat let nazad," Pravda, 1927 May 6 (Box-folder 3: 34)
- Badaev, A., "O Staline," Pravda, p. 3, a short biography sketch, 1939 December 19 (Box-folder 3: 35)
- Kom Pravda, biography sketch, 1929 December 21 (Box-folder 3: 36)
- London Conference - Stalin, 1965 (Box-folder 3: 37)
- Abromivich, R. G., "Genghis Khan of the 20th Century,", 1949 December 30 (Box-folder 3: 38)
- Dadiani, Shalva, "Istoricheskie mesta tbilisi," Pravda, p. 3, 1939 December 17 (Box-folder 3: 39)
- "Aliens Act of 1905," Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1956 (Box-folder 3: 40)
- Bokov, I., "Sila Stalina," Pravda, p. 5, 1939 December 24 (Box-folder 3: 41)
- Brussels Congress, 1904 (Box-folder 3: 42)
- "V novoye ude," Pravda, 1939 December 25 (Box-folder 3: 43)
- Photographs and facsimiles, 1967 (Box-folder 3: 44)
- Stalin materials, Lowenthal, undated (Box-folder 3: 45)
- Pacifism, a bibliography, 1960 March 2 (Box-folder 3: 46)
- Index to Stalin bibliography, undated (Box-folder 3: 47)
- Index card boxes (A-Z), 1960-1964 (Boxes 4-6)
  Written in English and Russian, the index cards include typed titles and excerpts from books published between 1899 and 1964.
- Photographs and negatives, undated (Box-folder 7: 1)
- Article clippings, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- Article clippings, death of Edward E. Smith, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 3)
- Buckelew, Alvin H., "An Analysis of the Mechanism Used by the Government of the United States for Dealing with National and International Terrorism,", 1981 (Box-folder 7: 4)
- Terphill, Frank, "Confessions of a Dangerous Man," Department of Defense, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 5)
- Tennant, Ellis, "An Enigma that Resolved Itself Perhaps," typed essay, 1960 (Box-folder 7: 6)
- "An Epilogue to the Mole Hunt," Newsweek, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 7)
- "The Human Intelligence Network Report," Independent Research and Information Systems Ltd., 1981 March 20 (Box-folder 7: 8)
- Molnar, Thomas, "Pursuit in Zurich,", 1976 July 1 (Box-folder 7: 9)
- Feiger, George, "Russian Scenes, Russian Voices," Reader's Digest, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 10)
- Safire, William, "Sand in My Shoes," The New York Times, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 11)
- Durbrow, Elbridge, "Soviet Aims, Neither Wholly a Riddle, nor Mystery, and Even Less an Enigma," Situation Report, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 12)
- "The Soviet State Budget Since 1965," National Foreign Assessment Center, 1977 (Box-folder 7: 13)
- Malan, Rian, "The Spies Among Us," Nine West, 1981 (Box-folder 7: 14)
- Epstein, Edward J., "The Spy Wars," The New York Times, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 15)
- "Is This American a Soviet Spy?," Reader's Digest, 1981 (Box-folder 7: 16)
- Biography, handwritten, undated (Box-folder 7: 17)
- Correspondence, 1950-1982 (Box-folder 7: 18)
- Correspondence, Williams, D. M. B., 1962 (Box-folder 7: 19)
- Dinner invitation from the Association of Former Intelligence Officers, San Francisco chapter, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 20)
- Letter of appreciation, from the Department of State, recognizing successful CIA mission in Moscow, 1950 (Box-folder 7: 21)
- National Security Agency personal documents, security investigation and employment information, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 7: 22)
- Personal contacts, 1981 (Box-folder 7: 23)
- Personal experience record, 1962 (Box-folder 7: 24)
- Speech preparation, outline and notes, 1961 (Box-folder 7: 25)
- Typed commentary regarding an interview with Russell Langelle and his recent expulsion from the USSR, undated (Box-folder 7: 26)
- "How Much is Soviet Gold?," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 7: 27)
- "A Preliminary Consideration of Social Problems within the Soviet Bloc of Nations," typed essay, 1957 (Box-folder 7: 28)
- "The Role of Covert Operations in Soviet Diplomacy," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 7: 29)
- "Smith Bellingham International Intelligence Survey," typed essay, 1981 August 1 (Box-folder 7: 30)
- "A Study in Pathos," typed essay regarding security of CIA agents abroad, 1960 May 14 (Box-folder 7: 31)
- Typescript from Izvestiya, 1963 March 12 (Box-folder 7: 32)
- Smith, Edward E., "The Role of Covert Operations in Soviet Diplomacy,", 1961 March 1 (Box-folder 8: 1)
- Alliluyev, "Moi vospominaniia," Krasnaiia Letopis, no. 5, 1923 (Box-folder 8: 2)
- A report on Kamo, Okhrana dossier, 1907 (Box-folder 8: 3)
- Stockholm Conference, Okhrana report, 1906 (Box-folder 8: 4)
- Stalin materials, undated (Box-folder 8: 5)
- Snegov, A. V., "Several Pages from the History of the Party," from March to the beginning of April 1917, undated (Box-folder 8: 6)
- Cieplinkski, Michael, 1964 April 10 (Box-folder 8: 7)
- Garnett, David, "The Golden Echo," Harcourt Brace, 1954 (Box-folder 8: 8)
- London Conference, British news accounts, 1907 (Box-folder 8: 9)
- London Conference, Okhrana agent report, 1907 (Box-folder 8: 10)
- The Department of Police and the Bolsheviks, undated (Box-folder 8: 11)
- Book reviews, 1964 (Box-folder 8: 12)
- Gilmore, Eddy, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 8: 13)
- Correspondence, Levine, Isaac D., 1960-1967 (Box-folder 8: 14)
- Stalin, Okhrana documents from Hoover, undated (Box-folder 8: 15)
- Smith, Edward E., "Tragedy of an American Diplomat,", 1963 (Box-folder 8: 16)
- Uncompleted outlines and writings, undated (Box-folder 8: 17)
- Julian, Thomas A., 1968 (Box-folder 8: 18)
- Leggett, George H., 1968-1969 (Box-folder 8: 19)
- Malinovsky, undated (Box-folder 8: 20)
- "St. Petersburg 1905-1909," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 8: 21)
- Kennan, George, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 8: 22)
- Souvarine, Boris, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 8: 23)
- Possony, Stefan T., 1964-1969 (Box-folder 8: 24)
- Siscoe, Frank G., 1968 (Box-folder 8: 25)
- Vano Nanuashvili, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 8: 26)
- Slusser, Robert M., John Hopkins University, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 8: 27)
- Diplomatic list, compiled by the British Embassy, Moscow, 1956 (Box-folder 9: 1)
- Speech note cards, 1972 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Speech note cards, 1974 (Box-folder 9: 3)
- Martyno, A. P., "Moia sluzhba v otdel'nom korpuse zhandarmov 1898-1917,", 1938 (Box-folder 9: 4-7)
  This memoir was copied and typed by Smith and includes his personal notes and grammatical corrections.
- Zhitomirsky reports to foreign agency, undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
- Typed comments, subject is the 1912 conference and passed resolutions regarding the Russian Social Democratic Labor Party, 1969 February 12 (Box-folder 10: 2)
- "Vypuskayut provokatorov!," Rabochy i Soldat, no. 14, 1917 August 8 (Box-folder 10: 3)
- "Antivoennaya rabota," Istorichesky Arkhiv, no. 5, 1961 (Box-folder 10: 4)
- "Iz zhizni i deatelnosti," Edinstvo, no. 5, p. 11-12, 1909 May 26 (Box-folder 10: 5)
- Malinovsky, R., "Strakhovanie ot," Edinstvo, no. 6, 1909 June 15 (Box-folder 10: 6)
- Badaev, A. E., "Pokhoron," Izvestiya, no. 261, p. 4, 1951 November 6 (Box-folder 10: 7)
- Cherepakhov, M. S., "Russian Periodicals 1895-1917," State Publishing House Political Literature, Moscow, 1957 (Box-folder 10: 8)
- Leninsky Sbornik, vol. XIII, Moscow, 1930 (Box-folder 10: 9)
- Kukhlin, N. I., "Nelegalnoe izdanie," Istorichesky Arkhiv, no. 4, 1960 (Box-folder 10: 10)
- "Zhandarmy o pravde," Proletarskaia Revoliutsiya, no. 14, 1923 (Box-folder 10: 11)
- "Vypuskayut provokatorov," Rabochy i soldat, no. 14, 1917 August (Box-folder 10: 12)
- Volodarskaya, A. M., "Podgotovka," Istorichesky Arkhiv, no. 6, 1958 (Box-folder 10: 13)
- Zharov and Kuznetsov, "O rodgotovke prazhskoi," Istoricheskii Arkhiv, 1958 (Box-folder 10: 14)
- Loginov, V. T. and G. B. Petryakov, "Deyetelnost tsk," Pravda, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 15)
- "Correspondence from Russian Social Democratic Labor Party and Local Party Organizations 1912-1914," Istoricheskii Arkhiv, 1960 (Box-folder 10: 16)
- Photographs for Taylor and the Truth, undated (Box-folder 10: 17)
- Loventhal, Milton, 1962 (Box-folder 10: 18)
- Malamuth, Charles, 1964 (Box-folder 10: 19)
- Hilger, Gustav, undated (Box-folder 10: 20)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 10: 21)
- "Sobranie chlenov obshchestva," Edinstvo, no. 13, 1910 January 15 (Box-folder 10: 22)
- Smith, Edward E., "The Tailor," chapter IV, Moscow, undated (Box-folder 10: 23)
- Smith, Edward E., "Success at Prague: The No. 2 Bolshevik," chapter IV, second version, undated (Box-folder 10: 24)
- Smith, Edward E., "Malinovsky's Election to the IV Duma: A Classic Okhrana Operation," chapter VII, undated (Box-folder 10: 25)
- Smith, Edward E., "Pravda," chapter VIII, 1968 (Box-folder 10: 26)
- Smith, Edward E., "The Fourth Duma and Mr. X, 1912-1913-1914: His Creeping Independence," chapter IX, undated (Box-folder 10: 27)
- Smith, Edward, chapter XI, undated (Box-folder 10: 28)
- Smith, Edward, chapter X, undated (Box-folder 10: 29)
- Smith, Edward, chapter X, second version, undated (Box-folder 10: 30)
- Smith, Edward E., "German POW: Work for Lenin and the German General Staff," Chapter IX, second version, undated (Box-folder 10: 31)
- Smith, Edward E., “A Voluntary Return to Death: The Trial and Execution of a Dual Personality, the First Communist Purge Trial,” chapter XIII, undated (Box-folder 10: 32)
- Marina's first testimony, Kennedy assassination, typed transcript, 1964 Feburary 3 (Box-folder 10: 33)
- "Comments on the Appeals of Communism,", 1961 Janurary 25 (Box-folder 10: 34)
- Testimony of N. S. Chkheidze, 1968 (Box-folder 10: 35)
- Notes, 1945 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  Includes Edward Smith's diary from 1945 when he worked in Germany before the end of World War II. Entries cover his work assisting lieutenants and daily reports.
- Possony, Stefan T., "The Polygraph and Resurrection,", 1965 February (Box-folder 11: 2)
- Possony, Stefan T. and Edward E. Smith, "The Warren Commission and Soviet Intelligence,", undated (Box-folder 11: 3)
- "The Foreign Policy Tradition," typed essay, 1961 (Box-folder 11: 4)
- Notes and research on the Soviet seizure of power from Georgia to Cuba, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 11: 5)
- Sorge Case, 1964 (Box-folder 11: 6)
- U.S.S.R. second quarter, 1974 (Box-folder 11: 7)
- Komintern fourth international, Ukrainian Rada, 1958 February 12 (Box-folder 11: 8)
- "Shadows of the Kremlin," preface, undated (Box-folder 11: 9)
- The Penkovskiy case, 1965 December 4 (Box-folder 11: 10)
- American Embassy Moscow, 1964 (Box-folder 11: 11)
- Peaceful coexistence, 1964 (Box-folder 11: 12)
- "A Crisis in United States Security?," an essay, undated (Box-folder 11: 13)
- Drafts and writings, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 11: 14)
  About the 1921 Chaikovskii Street and the Quiet Disaster.
- Potential projects, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 11: 15)
- U.S.S.R. newsclips, second quarter, 1972 (Box-folder 11: 16)
- "The CIA'S Goof in Assessing the Soviets," Business Week, 1977 February 28 (Box-folder 11: 17)
- Smith, Edward E., "Unilateral Space Observation by the U.S.S.R.,", undated (Box-folder 11: 18)
- "The Spy War," New York Times, 1980 September 28 (Box-folder 11: 19)
- "The Crisis in United States Internal Security," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 11: 20)
- Pincher, Chapman, "Spies in the Secret Service," Their Trade Is Treachery, 1982 (Box-folder 11: 21)
- "Agent Orange," The American Legion, and Durbrow, Elbridge, "Soviet Aims: Neither Wholly a Riddle, nor Mystery, and Even Less an Enigma," Situation Report, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 11: 22)
- Card file boxes (A-Z), 1961-1969 (Boxes 12-16)
  Cards include publication titles, selected excerpts, book summaries, and locations of publication photocopies. Subjects include Russian history and espionage from 1793-1962.
- Erenfeld, M., "Delo Malinovskogo" Voprosy Istorii, 1965 (Box-folder 17: 1)
- L. V., "Provokator Malinovsky (istoricheskaya spravka)," Edinstvo, no. 11, p. 2, 1917 April 12 (Box-folder 17: 2)
- "K delu Malinovskago," Edinstvo, no. 24, 1917 April 27 (Box-folder 17: 3)
- "Iz zhizni i deatelnosti" Edinstvo, no. 11, 1909 December 1 (Box-folder 17: 4)
- "Iz zhizni i deyatelnosti obshchestvo," Nadeshda, 1908 October 31 (Box-folder 17: 5)
- "The Russian Bureau of the Central Committee Correspondence with Foreign Countries during the War Years 1915-1916," Proletarskaia Revoliutsiia, 1930 (Box-folder 17: 6)
- "Luda," Pravda, no. 18, 1917 March 26 (Box-folder 17: 7)
- "Dela tsarskikh sanovnikov," Novoye Vedomosti (cevh. vyr.), 1918 June 20 (Box-folder 17: 8)